Joseph S. Kulmacz Papers VHP2004/14
CCSU Veterans History Project
Joseph S. Kulmacz Papers
1943 - 2004
VHP2004/14
CCSU Veterans History Project
124.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
Joseph S. Kulmacz, 1922 -
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph Kulmacz enlisted in the U.S. Navy in early 1943. Before enlisting in the Navy he worked at Pratt and Whitney in East Hartford, CT where he became familiar with working on aircraft. Due to his work experience Kulmacz was placed in the Naval Air Technical Training Center in Tennessee and later attended Aircraft and Mechanic School. He was trained as a flight engineer and was one of a crew of eleven that flew a PBM Martin Mariner seaplane. Kulmacz's squadron was first stationed in Leyte Gulf in the Philippines, where they saw combat, and flew patrol missions from the Philippines to French Indochina (what is now Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos), and then later from Mindoro to French Indochina. Typical patrols were over 12 hours long, and were mainly used for reconnaissance purposes. He returned to the United States in 1945, after V-J Day, and after being discharged, he returned to Pratt and Whitney, where he worked for 44 years as a process planner.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged based on content and material type into 4 series:
Series I, Personal papers
Series II, Military documents
Series III, Publications
Series IV, Multi-media
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
United States. Navy. Patrol Bomber Squadron. VP/VPB-25.; United States. Navy.; Banana River Naval Air Station (Fla.); Hawaii; Mariner bombers; Martin PBM-5 Mariner (Seaplane); Mindoro (Philippines); Naval Air Technical Training Center (Naval Air Station Memphis (Tenn.)); Philippines; United States. Navy--Machinist's mates; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Philippines; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2004/14.I
  - "Over-Here: Somewhere in the Philippines" Newsletter, 16 March 1945; VHP2004/4.I.01; 4.0 Digital objects
  - "Sacred Order of the Golden Dragon" (Shellback certificate),Certification of completed training, and Prayer for those in active service., 18 November 1944; VHP2004/14.I.02
  - Joseph Kulmacz’s permit to buy alcoholic beverages in state of Washington, Permit expires Sept. 30, 1946; VHP2004/14.I.03
  - Naval Air Station, Banana River, VPB 2 OTU3. Combat Air Crew certificate, March 11, 1944; VHP2004/14.I.04
  - Joseph Kuzmacz’s tags and awards, Circa 1940s; VHP2004/14.I.05
  - Japanese government-issued Philippine fiat peso, Circa 1940s; VHP2004/14.I.06
  - Japanese government-issued Philippine fiat peso, Circa 1940s; VHP2004/14.I.07
  - Japanese invasion money in Rupee, Yuan, Sen, Cent, Circa 1940s; VHP2004/14.I.08
  - Philippines 2 Pesos emergency circulating notes (guerrilla pesos),1 Dollar Canada and, 1 Yen Japanese military currency., Circa 1940s; VHP2004/14.I.09
  - Interview sysnopsis, November 22, 2004; VHP2004/14.I.10
- Series II: Military Papers, VHP2004/14.II
  - Registration Certificate and Description of Registrant, June 30, 1942; VHP2004/14.II.01
  - Certificate of completion of course at Naval Air Technical Training Center (Aviation Machinist Mate Course), October 6, 1943; VHP2004/14.II.02
  - Certificate of completion of course at Naval Air Gunners School, December 16, 1943; VHP2004/14.II.03
  - N.AER.4111 Aviators Flight Log Book, December 2, 1944 - August 1, 1945; VHP2004/14.II.04; 18.0 Digital objects
  - Notice of Separation from U.S. Naval Service, December 5, 1945; VHP2004/14.II.05; 18.0
  - issuance of Air Medal for Joseph Kulmacz, 1945; VHP2004/14.II.06; 18.0
  - Air Medal Award, June 9, 1947; VHP2004/14.II.07; 18.0
  - Gold Star in lieu of the Second Air Medal Award, Decomber 9, 1947; VHP2004/14.II.08; 18.0
  - Distinguished Flying Cross Award, December, 1947; VHP2004/14.II.09; 18.0
  - Translated text in case of emergency, carried by Americans, n.d.; VHP2004/14.II.010; 18.0
  - Map of Philippine Islands, VHP2004/14.II.11; 18.0
  - Map of Philippine Islands, VHP2004/14.II.12; 18.0
  - Map of Philippine Islands, VHP2004/14.II.13; 18.0
  - Map of Taiwan, n.d.; VHP2004/14.II.14; 18.0
  - Map of Philippine Islands, VHP2004/14.II.15; 18.0
  - Map of Taiwan and Luzon, VHP2004/14.II.16; 18.0
- Series III: Publications, VHP2004/14.III
  - Navy Log, n.d.; VHP2004/14.III.01; 38.0 Digital objects
  - Newspaper Article: Woman Who Hid Yanks Held Prisoner 9 Years, Circa 1950s; VHP2004/14.III.02; 38.0 Digital objects
  - Newspaper Article: Vietnam Woman Sought by Ensign She Shelted, 1954; VHP2004/14.III.03; 38.0
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2004/14.IV
  - Subseries A: Still Images
    - Joseph Kulmacz and sister, Florence, 1925 - New Britain, CT, VHP2004/14.IV.01; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz in Navy uniform, 1943, VHP2004/14.IV.02; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz and sister,Florence, March 1943 - New Britain, CT, VHP2004/14.IV.03; 38.0
    - Home from Boot Camp, Joseph Kulmacz, March 1943 - New Britain, CT, VHP2004/14.IV.04; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz and sister, Maria, March 1943 - New Britain, CT, VHP2004/14.IV.05; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz and sister, Florence, March 1943 - New Britain, CT, VHP2004/14.IV.06; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz and his buddy, Tony Stregowski, March 1943 - New Britain,CT, VHP2004/14.IV.07; 38.0
    - Boot Camp, March 1943 - New Port, RI. Left to right rear: George Juvell, Joe Kulmacz Middle: Jess Humple, unknown, Harold Hoglund Front: Samuel Hussok, VHP2004/14.IV.08; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz, June 1943 - Memphis, TN, VHP2004/14.IV.09; 38.0
    - Left to right: Micholwski - U.S. Navy - Sea Bees John Kawacki - U.S. Army Joe Kulmacz - U.S. Navy March 1943, VHP2004/14.IV.10; 38.0
    - Left to right: William McBee, Unknown, Joe Kulmacz. Hertford, NC, 1943; VHP2004/14.IV.11; 38.0
    - Air strip at Johnston Island, Pacific Ocean., Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.12; 38.0
    - Martin PBM Mariner airplane, Johnston Island, Pacific Ocean., Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.13; 38.0
    - William McBee and Joe Kulmacz on U.S.S Copahee, CVE, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.14; 38.0
    - Kaneohe Bay, HA Left to right: Eddie Norton, Longo, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.15; 38.0
    - Hawaii. Left to right: McBee, Kulmacz, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.16; 38.0
    - “Beer Party” Left to right: John Martin, William McBee, Tom Ray, Jack Hatcher, Joe Kulmacz Rest are unknown, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.17; 38.0
    - “Beer Party” Left to right: Jack Hatcher, Anthony Longo, Thomas Ray Front: Joe Kulmacz, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.18; 38.0
    - “Beer Party” Left to right: Jack Hatcher, Anthony Longo, Thomas Ray Front: Joe Kulmacz, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.19; 38.0
    - The Philippines - Crew #1 Rear: William McBee, Francis Mitchell, Thomas Ray, Anthony Longo, Joseph Kulmacz Front: Chief John Martin, Ensign Charles Rudgers, Chief Jack Hatcher, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.20; 38.0
    - Secret mission: smoke fire to signal where to land - Philippines, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.21; 38.0
    - Secret mission: picking up Japanese prisoners - Philippines, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.22; 38.0
    - Secret mission: picking up Japanese prisoners - Philippines, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.23; 38.0
    - Secret mission: smoke fire to signal where to land - Philippines, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.24; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz changing a spark plug on PBM 3D. Banana River, FL, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.25; 38.0
    - Joe Micholowski in diving suit, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.26; 38.0
    - Postcard of Martin PBM-3, Mariner, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.27; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz receiving Distingushed Flying Cross - Whidbey Island, WA, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.28; 38.0
    - Receiving Distingushed Flying Cross - Whidbey Island, WA, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.29; 38.0
    - PBM Mariner “Diamond” coming aboard the Norton Sound, 1946, VHP2004/14.IV.30; 38.0
    - Operational Training at Banana River, FL Left to right rear: Julius Tlustohowich, Ensign Barber, Ensign Wright, Ensign Gilbert, Erving Eisenberg Front: O.L. Hammond, William Zumbrum, Edgar Josephsen, John Pritz, Robert Truesdale, Joseph Kulmacz, Circa 1940; VHP2004/14.IV.31; 38.0
    - Joseph Kulmacz, March 20, 2006, VHP2004/14.IV.32; 38.0
  - Subseries B: Moving Images
    - Oral History Interview, VHP2004/14.IV.B.1; 1.0 dvd (Disk DVD VHP2004/14, Box VHP Interview 1)
      Existence and Location of Copies note
      Interview video also available online.
      Streaming Video